Guide to the Episcopal Churchpeople for a Free Southern Africa Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Episcopal Churchpeople for a Free Southern Africa Records
1961-1998
RG 102
Yale University Divinity School Library
3.5
(8 boxes)
The records in this collection primarily document the ECFSA's work in relation to Namibia. The ECFSA has served as a link between Anglicans in Southern Africa and people in the United States by publishing a newsletter, issuing news releases, sponsoring public meetings, preparing and publishing special reports, sponsoring speaking and study tours for Southern Africans, raising funds to support education and provide relief in Southern Africa, and providing aid and counsel to visiting Southern Africans. The organization has encouraged its supporters to contact U.S. political leaders regarding crucial issues.
Episcopal Churchpeople for a Free Southern Africa
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the ECFSA.
Biographical / Historical
1956 Episcopal Churchmen for South Africa, an organization of Episcopal laypeople, was founded, with headquarters in New York City "to support the work and witness of the Anglican Church of the Province of South Africa, particularly as it faces the doctrine and practice of apartheid."
1966 The international territory of Namibia, formerly known as South West Africa, was a mandate of the United Nations. In 1966 the U.N. stripped the Republic of South Africa of legal authority in the territory, but South Africa maintained de facto control over Namibia and continued to work toward annexation of the territory.
1968 Jan 25 Bishop Robert Mize was advised by South African Department of the Interior that his residence permit would expire in July 1968
1968 Sep 1 The African community of the Old Location at Windhoek, capital of Namibia, was forced to evacuate by the South African government.
1971Jun 21 World Court affirmed South Africa's presence in Namibia to be illegal and asked that the United Nations not recognize So. Africa's presence and administration
1971 Jun 30 Evangelical Lutheran Ovambo-kavango Church (ELOC) and Evangelical Lutheran Church (ELC) Bishops wrote an open letter to the Prime Minister asking South Africa to withdraw from Namibia on the basis of Human Rights violations
1971 Jul 25 Anglican Bishop Colin O'Brien Winter wrote statement in Support of ELC/ELOC letter
1971 Dec 13 General strike of African workers begun by contract laborers spread throughout country
1972 Feb Bishop Winter and two white assistants, Father S.F. Hayes and David de Beer, received deportation orders to leave Namibia by March 4 at noon
1972 Mar 6 UN Secretary General Kurt Waldheim visited So. Africa to talk to government about Namibia
1972 Apr 2 UN Security Council passed two resolutions reaffirming the occupation of Namibia as illegal and calling for conditions to enable the independence of Namibia
1975 Jun 16 Richard Wood (elected Suffragan Bishop in Damaraland after expulsion of Bishop Winter in 1972) received deportation order to leave Namibia by June 23
1975 Jun 22 Bishop-in-Exile Winter ordained Roger Key and Edward Morrow and admitted James Kauluma as a deacon in England
1975 Sep Kauluma began studies at Union Theological Seminary, NY
1977 ECSA filed requests under the Freedom of Information Act with eight U.S. government agencies for disclosure of their relations with the South African Bureau for State Security.
1977 May Anglican, Lutheran, and Roman Catholic Churches made a joint statement on torture in Namibia
1977 Oct 12 Kauluma ordained as Priest in NY and elected as Bishop Suffragan following resignation of Bishop Richard Wood
1978 Jan 17 Consecration of Kauluma as Bishop Suffragan Elect, the first black Bishop in Namibia1978 JulRev. Edward Morrow, Anglican vicar general, his wife Laureen, and Rev. Heinz Hunke, provincial superior of Roman Catholic order of Mary Immaculate, received orders to leave Namibia within seven days
1978 Council of Churches in Namibia (CCN) formed
1979 May 16 Eight So. African Security Police raided and searched CCN offices looking for "banned literature"
1980 Reports of a death squad and death list organized by So. African government to kill prominent citizens
1980 Nov 19 Bombing of printing press of ELOC at Oniipa, Namibia, (had been previously sabotaged on May 11, 1973)
1981 Jun 18 Bombing of Anglican Mission Seminary Buildings at Odibo, Namibia
1983Feb 16 The Executive Committee of the CCN sent two open letters: one to Members of the Western Contact Group and one to the Prime Minister of the Republic of South Africa
1984 Episcopal Churchmen for South Africa changed its name to Episcopal Churchpeople for a Free Southern Africa
1984 Mar Anglican, ELOC, and Roman Catholic leaders helped direct a court application for the release of 37 detainees abducted by So. African Defence Forces in a raid on Angola 6 years previously
1986 Jan 23 Arson fire destroyed CCN offices
1986 Apr 29-30 CCN meeting of major political and community groups that support UN resolution 435, resulted in the Ai-gams declaration
1987Aug German Evangelical Lutheran Church withdrew from CCN
1989 CCN continued to work towards independence in conjunction with UN forces and others
1990Jan 29-30 Namibian Core-group met in Switzerland, including representatives from WCC and CCN to celebrate successful implementation of UN Resolution 435, completion of repatriation of Namibian exiles, peaceful elections, and the development of a draft for a Namibian Constitution and to discuss future needs and problems
1990 Mar 21 Namibia officially declared independent from South Africa
Scope and Contents
While the ECFSA publications in Series V document its work throughout Southern Africa, the materials in the first four series relate primarily to the Namibian situation. The majority of the files in these series date from 1970 to 1990.
This record group provides valuable documentation of the political and religious situation in Southern Africa during the past three decades. The ECFSA newsletters and special reports, in particular, provide extensive factual information and analysis of the situation. ECFSA efforts to influence U.S. government policy toward South Africa are also documented. The extensive files relating to the Council of Churches and other church groups and organizations in Namibia provide detailed, grassroots documentation of events and situations. Since the offices of the Council of Churches in Namibia suffered an arson fire in 1986, some of the documents in these files may not be accessible elsewhere. Individual files for several African church leaders document their activities and influence.
Arrangement
I. Namibia Files - Council of Churches in Namibia, 1971-1990
II. Namibia Files - Church Groups and Organizations, 1965-1990, n.d
III. Namibia Files - Individual files. 1961-1990
IV. Topical files, 1974-1990, n.d.
V. Publications of ECSA/ECFSA, 1963-1998, n.d.
South Africa -- Foreign relations -- United States; United States -- Foreign relations -- South Africa; Episcopal Church -- Missions -- Africa, Southern; Episcopal Churchpeople for a Free Southern Africa
- Namibia Files - Council of Churches in Namibia, 1971-1990; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Material relating to the formation of the Council of Churches in Namibia is followed by chronologically arranged files documenting its activities.
  - Churches in Namibia (process of forming CCN), 1971, 1972, 1974-1985, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Council of Churches in Namibia (CCN), 1977-1982, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - CCN: support of foreign churches, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CCN, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - CCN: application, prisoners, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - CCN, 1985-1986 n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - CCN Meeting, April 29-30, 1986: AI-GAMS Declaration, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - CCN, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 14-18)
- Namibia Files: Churches and Organizations, 1965-1990, n.d.; Series II
  The documentation in this series is arranged alphabetically by organization.
  - A.M.E. Church, 1979-1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Amnesty International, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Anglican Church: Conference center, 1981-1985, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Anglican Church: Diocese of Damaraland, 1971-1990, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
  - Anglican Church: History inquiry, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Anglican Church: Multiracial School, Windhoek, 1975-1984 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Anglican Church: St. Mary's Church, Onekwaya, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Anglican Church: Support for, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Chaplaincy, 1976-1983, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Christian Center in Namibia, 1976-1978, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Churches Union, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - International Freedom Council, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Lutheran Church: Evangelical Fellowship of Namibia in SWA/Namibia (EFSWAN) (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Lutheran Church: Evangelical Lutheran Church (ELC), 1978-1989, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Lutheran Church: Evangelical Lutheran Ovambo-kavango Church (ELOC), 1983, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Lutheran Church in Namibia, 1965-1983, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 36-37)
  - Lutheran Church statements, 1978-1985, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Lutheran Church: Martin Luther High School, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Namibia Women's Voice, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - "Namibia Report: Report of the Archbishop of Canterbury's Delegation to the Diocese of Namibia", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Roman Catholic Church, 1983-1989, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - South African Christian Alliance, 1990, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - United Christian Action, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - World Council of Churches, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Young South Africans for a Christian Civilization, 1984-1989 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Youth for Christ, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 47)
- Namibia Files: Individual Files, 1961-1990; Series III
  The documentaiton in this series is arranged alphabetically by individual.
  - Dumeni, Kleopas (Bishop), 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Frederick, Hendrik (Bishop), 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Kameeta, Zephaniah (Pastor), 1975-1990, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Kauluma, James (Bishop), 1961-1990, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 51-53)
  - Keruaera, B. G. (Rev.), 1972-1987 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Muafangejo, John, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Roberts, Alun, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Shejavali, Abisai (Rev.), 1977-1988 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Shilongo, Philip, 1973-1990 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Witbooi, Hendrik (Pastor), 1984 (Box 5, Folder 59)
- Topical Files, 1974-1990,n.d.; Series IV
  The Topical Files are arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Attack on churches, 1974-1990 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Bombing at Oniipa of ELOC press, 1980-1984, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Bombing at St. Mary's Seminary building, Odibo, Ovamboland, 1974-1986 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Churches -- Proximity Talks, March 1979 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Church hospitals, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Clippings: including articles by Tom Wicker and Sally Quinn, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Clippings: Anglican Church and Namibia, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Death threats, 1980, 1989, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - "German Namibian History," by Hermann Sinram, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Pro Pretoria Churches, 1979-1981 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Religious Right during implementation, 1987-1990, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - RSA - SADF investigation of churches, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 71)
- Publications of the ECSA/ECFSA, 1963-1998; Series V
  The publications are arranged chronologically.
  - Newsletters, Financial Appeal for Ovamboland, and Financial Appeal for the Church in Basutoland, 1963-1973, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Newsletters, 1974-1978 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Newsletters and "Testament of a Namibian Woman: Rauna Nambinga", 1979-1981 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Newsletters, "One Step -- in the Wrong Direction: the Sullivan Principles as a Strategy for Opposing Apartheid" by Elizabeth Schmidt, and "Security Police Abuses of Political Detainees" by the Detainees' Parents Support Committee, 1982-1986 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Newsletters, 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Newsletters and "Security Council Resolution 435" by the Lawyers Committee for Civil Rights Under Law, Washington, DC, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Newsletters, 1990-1992 (Box 7, Folder 78-80)
  - Newsletters, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Newsletters and Prayer Cards, 1994-1998, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 82)